Finding Aid for School of Education (University of Michigan) Records, 1904-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Dean's Files
  - Cecil Miskel, 1980-1998; 1988-1993
    - Taubman, A. Alfred
      - 4/11/1994 (Box 78)
      - Blackmond, Harrison, 3/29/1993 (Box 78)
      - Project, 10/7/1993 (Box 78)
    - Taylor, Suzanne Email (Box 79)
      - 1992-1993 (Box 79)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 79)
    - Teacher Certification
      - Correspondence/Email, 1995 (Box 79)
      - Project, 1995 (Box 79)
    - Teacher Education
      - Committee, 1989 (Box 79)
      - Study Group and Task Force, 3/22/1990 (Box 79)
    - Teacher Competency Testing, 1992-1993; 2 folders (Box 79)
    - Teacher Preparation Merit School Committee, 1990-1995 (Box 79)
    - Title V
      - Current Law & Funding History, Undated (Box 79)
      - General, 1992 (Box 79)
      - Testimony, 1991; 2 folders (Box 79)
    - Tuition Return Agreement, 8/1993 (Box 79)
    - University Council for Educational Administration (UCEA)
      - National Graduate Student Seminar, 1989 (Box 79)
      - Proposal Reviews, 6/1992 (Box 79)
      - Site Visit-Dick Rossmiller, 1989 (Box 79)
    - United States Russian Task Force Meeting, 1992 (Box 79)
    - United States Senate Subcommittee on Postsecondary Education, 1990-1991 (Box 79)
    - University Council on International Academic Affairs
      - 1990-1991 (Box 79)
      - 1991-1992 (Box 79)
    - University Libraries Correspondence, 1989-1990; 1990-1991 (Box 79)
    - University Relations
      - General, 1991 (Box 79)
      - 1991-1992 (Box 79)
    - University Seminar, 10/27-10/29; 1994 (Box 79)
    - Vest, Cosovish, Gibson, Dinner with, 1989 (Box 79)
    - Vice President for Gov't Relations and Secretary of the University, Office of, 1989-1990 (Box 79)
    - Vice President for Research
      - Undated (Box 79)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 79)
    - Visiting Committee
      - Undated (Box 79)
      - 1991-1992 (Box 79)
      - Team, 1990 (Box 79)
    - Visiting Scholars Misc. (1993) (Box 80)
    - Warden, Eric Email
      - 1992-1993 (Box 80)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 80)
    - Washtenaw Agreement, 1990-1991 (Box 80)
    - Welcome to Michigan, 1993 (Box 80)
    - Whitaker, Gilbert R.
      - Annual Review
        - 7/24/1992 (Box 80)
        - 7/26/1993 (Box 80)
        - 7/29/1994 (Box 80)
      - Correspondence
        - 1992-1993 (Box 80)
        - 1993-1994 (Box 80)
        - 1994-1995 (Box 80)
      - Email
        - 1992-1993 (Box 80)
        - 1993-1994 (Box 80)
        - 1994-1995 (Box 80)
- School of Education Review, 1982-1984
  The School of Education Review series (4 linear feet) discusses in detail the lengthy and traumatic review of the School of Education which led to a Regental decision to significantly reduce the school's funding. Following a major shortfall in the 1981-82 state appropriation to the university, Provost Billy E. Frye announced a five-year plan to balance the budget by reductions of 10% spread across the campus and by selective major reductions from a few units targeted for downsizing and possible elimination. Units identified as candidates for major reduction and possible elimination were the School of Education, School of Art, and School of Natural Resources. A review committee was appointed in 1982 and began evaluating the School of Education's programs and its relevance to the university's mission. Public hearings were held in the fall of 1982 in which 86 individuals provided testimony regarding the School. The School supplied 10 volumes of detailed data and more than 200 exhibits. The review committee also interviewed faculty and staff both within and outside of the School as well as deans at four other schools of education. In March 1983 the review committee submitted its report containing 18 recommendations including a 40% cut in the School's budget over a five-year period which was endorsed by the Regents.
  The Review series has been divided into three sub-series: Official Document; Supplemental Records; and Memos, Correspondence, and Miscellaneous. Official Documents include the records that were provided to the Regents, such as the formal charge to the review committee, material supplied to that committee by the School of Education, public testimony, the review committee report, and the School's extensive response to the report. The file is arranged chronologically. Supplemental Records are the working papers of the dean's office, created while preparing the various official documents and exhibits the School submitted. It also includes information regarding the School's attitudes and strategies as the review process continued. The Supplemental Records are arranged alphabetically by topic. Additional material relating to the review was received in 1998 and is located in Boxes 47 and 48. Audio tapes of the public hearings are located in Box 42.
  Addition School of Education Review records were received in a later accession (in box 48). It consists of correspondence and communications among the faculty and Dean Stark and between Stark and the university administration, as well as letters of support from constituents of the school from around the country. It also contains transcripts of review hearing testimony, and summaries of review testimony.
  - Official Documents
    - Review Committee Charge (includes School's Response to Charge, February 1983), April 1982 (Box 12)
    - Material Supplied to Review Committee by SOE, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Public Testimony, October 26-November 3, 1982
      - Transcripts, 4 folders (Box 12)
        (audio tapes in box 42)
      - Supporting Documents (Box 12)
    - Review Committee Report
      - Original Draft, February 1983 (Box 12)
      - Final Report, February 25, 1983 (Box 12)
    - SOE Response to Report
      - Response (includes index to exhibits) (Box 12)
      - Exhibits
        - No. 1-25 (Box 12)
        - No. 26-37 (Box 13)
        - No. 38-50 (Box 13)
        - No. 51-66 (Box 13)
        - No. 67, 3 folders (Box 13)
        - No. 68-75 (Box 13)
        - No. 76-77 (Box 13)
        - No. 78 (Box 13)
        - No. 79-87 (Box 13)
        - No. 88-99 (Box 13)
        - No. 100-109 (Box 14)
        - No. 110-129 (Box 14)
        - No. 130-138 (Box 14)
        - No. 139-153 (Box 14)
        - No. 154 (Box 14)
        - No. 155-162 (Box 14)
      - Special Exhibits
        - "Big 10" Comparative Data (Box 14)
        - Education as a Professional School (Box 14)
        - Review of Educational Units (Box 14)
    - Public Hearing, April 20, 1983 (Box 14)
    - Vice-President for Academic Affairs Recommendations to Regents, September 1983 (Box 14)
    - Development Plan, February 1984 (Box 14)
    - Presentation to Central Administration, August 1984 (Box 14)
  - Supplemental Records
    - General (Box 14)
    - Alumni and Friends, 1982 (Box 14)
    - Budget Conferences, 1979-1982 (Box 15)
    - Budget Priorities Committee Report, April 1983 (Box 15)
    - Cross Campus Collaboration, 1979-82 (Box 15)
    - Curriculum Analysis, 1979 (Box 15)
    - Education Facts, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Exhibits
      - Supporting Data, 1982-1983 (Box 15)
      - General (Box 15)
      - Unused Documents (Box 15)
    - Faculty
      - Journals in Which Published, 1973-1980 (Box 15)
      - Meeting re Review Report, March 6, 1983 (Box 15)
      - Professional Association Memberships, 1980 (Box 15)
      - Workload, 1981 (Box 15)
      - Workshop, 1984 (Box 15)
    - Hearings (review), 1982
      - Analysis of (Box 15)
      - Speakers (Box 15)
    - Liaison Committee
      - General, 1982 (Box 15)
      - Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 15)
      - Minutes, 1982-1983 (Box 15)
    - Masters Survey, Questions 43 and 48 (Box 15)
    - Physical Education Review, June 18, 1983 (Box 15)
    - Programs
      - Goals and Objectives (Box 15)
      - Profiles of Specific Programs (Box 15)
      - Higher Education, Center for the Study of (faculty publications) (Box 16)
      - Education and Psychology, Combined Program, 1982 (Box 16)
    - Rackham Dissertation Reviews, Analysis of, 1982 (Box 16)
    - Reports
      - General, 1982 (Box 16)
      - Placement of Newly Certified Teachers, 1980 (Box 16)
      - Teacher Employment Patterns, 1977/78-1979/80 (Box 16)
      - GRE Report by Program at Ph.D. Level, 1982 (Box 16)
    - Task Forces
      - General (Box 16)
      - Membership (Box 16)
      - Curriculum, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - Implementation of Transition Plan (Box 16)
      - Institutional Policy (Box 16)
      - Research Center (Box 16)
      - Teacher Certification (Box 16)
  - Memos, Correspondence, and Miscellaneous
    - "Bad News" File (includes memos to staff potentially affected by cuts), 1982 (Box 48)
    - Communications from Dean Stark, 1982-1983 (Box 48)
    - Communications with University Administration, 1982-1983 (Box 48)
    - Canvass for Support
      - 1982-1983, 2 folders (Box 48)
      - Professional Organizations, 1982 (Box 48)
      - Review Mailing (after review report), 1983 (Box 48)
      - Information Sent to Constituents, 1982-1983 (Box 48)
    - Internal Communication, 1982-1983 (Box 48)
    - Letters of Support
      - 1982 (Box 48)
      - 1982-1983, 2 folders (Box 48)
      - Center for the Study of Higher Education, 1982 (Box 48)
      - Letters of Support Received Before Last Public Hearing, 1983 (Box 48)
      - Letters of Support Classified by Central Thrust, 1982 (Box 48)
    - Miscellaneous, 1979-1983 (Box 48)
    - Newspaper Articles, 1982-1983 (Box 48)
    - Press Correspondence, 1983 (Box 48)
    - Review Hearings--Planning and Administration, 1982 (Box 48)
    - Review Testimony Summaries, 1982 (Box 48)
    - Strategy Development, 1981-1983 (Box 48)
    - Testimony, 1982 (Box 48)
    - University of Michigan Articles, Speeches and Publications, 1977-1983 (Box 48)
- Associate Deans
  The Associate Dean's series (3.5 linear feet) is comprised of the papers of three associate deans, in tenure order: Charles F. Lehmann, Frederick W. Bertolaet, and Carl F. Berger. The papers of Charles F. Lehmann are relatively brief, but provide a very rich source of Building Committee materials, spanning the years 1922-1966. The bulk of the remaining materials consist of evaluations and reports critiquing the School of Education. The records created by Associate Dean Frederick W. Bertolaet are arranged alphabetically and are most notable for information on the subject of urban education (through various file headings such as "Detroit Public Schools", "Shaw College", and the "Urban Education Program") and on the internal organization of the School in 1969-1970. The Carl F. Berger materials, which are also relatively brief, are most interesting for the Program/Committee materials detailing the state of each program ca. 1979 and also the deliberations of the School's Research Committee, 1979-1980.
  - Lehmann, Charles
    - General, 1940-1971 (Box 16)
    - Building Committee
      - General
        - 1922-1945 (Box 16)
        - 1954-1955 (Box 16)
        - 1956-1958 (Box 16)
        - 1960-1966 (Box 16)
      - Opinion Poll, 1966 (Box 16)
    - By-Laws, 1956-1986 (Box 16)
    - Enrollment Statistics, 1952-1969 (Box 16)
    - Evaluation of Faculty Services, Committee on (report), 1942 (Box 16)
    - Goals/Purpose, 1941 (Box 16)
    - Reports
      - The Credibility of the Credit Hour-A Critique of the Credit System-History, Use, Shortcomings, 1970 (Box 16)
      - Report of the Committee to Evaluate Teachers Preparation Programs of the Secondary Level, undated (Box 16)
      - Report on the School of Education, University of Michigan, 1969 (Box 16)
    - Self Survey Committee, 1942 (Box 16)
    - Student Opinion Questionnaire (analysis of), 1938 (Box 16)
    - Transfer Students, 1957-1962 (Box 16)
    - University School Closing, 1969; 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Bertolaet, Frederick W.
    - Assistant Dean for Instruction Workbook, 1974/75 (Box 16)
    - Candidacy Committee, 1975 (Box 16)
    - Certification of Teachers, 1972-1976 (Box 16)
    - Cooperative Education, Task Force on, 1974 (Box 16)
    - Coordinator of Student Activities, 1973 (Box 16)
    - Courses-C300, 1972-1974 (Box 16)
    - Curriculum and Program Review, Task Force on, 1973-1974 (Box 17)
    - Day Care Program, 1970-1977 (Box 17)
    - Deans-Council of Eight, 1978 (Box 17)
    - Deans-Michigan "Big Six,", 1973-1977 (Box 17)
    - Deans/Chairpersons (SOE) (minutes), 1977-1978 (Box 17)
    - Deans and Directors (Michigan Colleges), 1976-1978 (Box 17)
    - Detroit Public Schools
      - Committee on Decentralization, 1977-1978 (Box 17)
      - University of Michigan Liaison Committee, 1970-1978; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Division Chairmen (SOE), 1970-1974 (Box 17)
    - Directed Teaching
      - 1970 (Box 17)
      - 1975-1976 (Box 17)
    - Doctoral Program Review, 1975 (Box 17)
    - Early Childhood Development and Education, Center of, 1974-1977 (Box 17)
    - Education Library (UGLI), 1973 (Box 17)
    - Education Task Force from Higher Education, 1973-1974 (Box 17)
    - Energy Conservation Committee, 1974 (Box 17)
    - Evaluation (SOE)
      - Phase I, 1975-1976; 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Phase II, 1976-1977 (Box 17)
    - Extension, 1975-1976 (Box 17)
    - Faculty
      - Forum, 1973-1974 (Box 17)
      - Workload Study, 1974 (Box 17)
    - Fees, 1974-1975 (Box 17)
    - Fiftieth Anniversary Celebration (SOE), 1971 (Box 17)
    - Financial Aid, 1976-1978 (Box 17)
    - Five Year Program Plan, 1974-1975; 3 folders (Box 17)
    - General Information re Secondary Directed Teaching, 1977 (Box 17)
    - Graduate Employees Organization (GEO), 1975-1976 (Box 17)
    - Graduate Programs, Committee for the Study of, 1975 (Box 17)
    - Graduate Requirements, Commission on (LSA), 1973 (Box 17)
    - In-service Education, 1977 (Box 18)
    - Institutional Research, Office of
      - 1968-1971 (Box 18)
      - 1971-1973 (Box 18)
    - Instructional Television, Committee on, 1971-1972 (Box 18)
    - Interpersonal and Organizational Change, 1972 (Box 18)
    - Internship, Committee on, 1976 (Box 18)
    - Lewis Business College, 1974-1975 (Box 18)
    - Library Committee, 1972-1974 (Box 18)
    - Library Council (UM), 1977 (Box 18)
    - Literary College (LSA), 1977-1978 (Box 18)
    - Long Range Planning, 1974 (Box 18)
    - Michigan Educational Association, 1970-1972 (Box 18)
    - Michigan Department of Education
      - General, 1969-1976; 5 folders (Box 18)
      - Legislature, 1969-1974 (Box 18)
    - Minority Affairs, Chicano Students, 1974 (Box 18)
    - Model Cities Program, 1970 (Box 18)
    - Mott Foundation and Program, 1973-1978; 2 folders (Box 18)
    - National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education, 1977 (Box 18)
    - National Conference of Professors of Educational Administration, 1978 (Box 18)
    - Oakland Teacher Education Council, 1972-1973 (Box 18)
    - Occupational Education Program Review, 1972-1973 (Box 18)
    - Off-Campus Television Committee, 1971 (Box 18)
    - Phi Delta Kappa, 1978-1979 (Box 18)
    - Phi Kappa Phi, 1965-1975 (Box 18)
    - Record Keeping and Information Systems (SOE), 1972-1976 (Box 18)
    - Registration Materials (SOE), 1978 (Box 18)
    - Reorganization (SOE)
      - Charts (undated) (Box 18)
      - Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 18)
      - Final Draft Proposal, April 7, 1970 (Box 18)
      - Proposals, 1970 (Box 18)
      - Voting, 1970 (Box 18)
    - Salary Disclosure Study, 1973 (Box 18)
    - Saudi Arabian Program, 1978 (Box 18)
    - School Library Media Program, Advisory Board, 1973 (Box 18)
    - Self Evaluation Study Committee, Rehabilitation Act of, 1973; 1978 (Box 18)
    - Shaw College, 1973-1976; 3 folders (Box 18)
      (See Also Urban Education Program)
    - Special Education Review Committee, 1973-1974 (Box 18)
    - Special Fields Committee, 1972-1974 (Box 18)
    - Social Work, 1971-1974 (Box 19)
    - Student Advising Office, 1969-1970 (Box 19)
    - Student Faculty Assembly, 1971 (Box 19)
    - Student Government Council, 1976 (Box 19)
    - Teacher Center Conference, 1974 (Box 19)
    - Teacher Corps, 1969-1971 (Box 19)
    - Teacher Education
      - Joint Committee, Ann Arbor Public Schools and UM, 1969 (Box 19)
      - Task Force for Innovation in (includes minutes), 1972-1976 (Box 19)
    - Teacher Education and Certification, Committee on, 1972-1974 (Box 19)
    - Teacher Preparation and Professional Development, Advisory Council for, 1976-1979; 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Teacher Supply and Demand, Advisory Council, 1973-1975 (Box 19)
    - University Council for Educational Administration, 1977-1978 (Box 19)
    - Urban Education Program
      (See Also-Shaw College)
      - General, 1969-1971; 1973-1975; 3 folders (Box 19)
      - Policy Board, 1973-1974 (Box 19)
    - WPA Adult Education Workshop (teachers workbook), 1938
      - Annual Reports, SOE, 1971-1973 (Box 19)
      - Bork, Alfred, 1979 (Box 19)
      - C-S (primarily 1979), 1978-1980 (Box 19)
      - Stark, Joan S., Dean, 1978-1980 (Box 19)
      - U-Z, 1979-1980 (Box 19)
      - Memo of Understanding with Office of Academic Planning and Analysis
        - Berger Draft, January 31, 1978 (Box 19)
        - Office of Academic Planning and Analysis Draft, February 6, 1978 (Box 19)
    - Program/Committee Files
      - General, 1979-1980 (Box 19)
      - A Program (Social Foundations), 1979 (Box 19)
      - B Program (Administration and Supervision), 1979 (Box 19)
      - C Program (Educational Psychology), 1979 (Box 19)
      - D Program (Curriculum and Instruction), 1979 (Box 19)
      - E Program (Occupational Education), 1979-1980 (Box 19)
      - F Program (Physical Education), undated (Box 19)
      - G Program (Higher Education), 1979 (Box 19)
      - H Program (Adult Education), 1979 (Box 19)
      - J Program (Guidance and Counseling), 1979 (Box 19)
      - M Program (Education and Community Development), 1979 (Box 19)
      - N Program (Speech Education), 1979-1980 (Box 19)
      - S Program (Speech and Hearing Sciences), 1979-1980 (Box 19)
  - Berger, Carl F.
    - Evaluation and Planning Study, 1975-1977; 2 folders (Box 19)
      (university-wide study)
- Audio-Visual Material
  The Audio-Visual Material series includes audio tapes, photographs, and videotapes. The audio material is comprised of an original set and a duplicate set of twenty-five audio tapes that are from the public testimony of the School of Education Review public hearings from October 26, 1982-November 3, 1982 and April 20, 1983. Transcripts from the hearings are available in Box 12. Also included in the Audio-visual series are two cassettes of conversations between Joan Stark and Carl Berger in February and May of 1984.
  The photograph files contains photographs from two School of Education events in 1972 - the 50th anniversary celebration and Lawrence Conrey's retirement celebration. The videotape is a VHS cassette of the School of Education's 75th anniversary celebration in 1997.
  - Audio Tapes
    - School of Education Review, Tape recordings of Testimony, October 26-November 2, 1982; April 20, 1983; 25 audiocassettes (Box 42)
      (Transcripts in box 12)
    - Interview, Joan Stark and Carl Berger, 1984; 2 audiocassettes (Box 42)
  - Photographs
    - Lawrence Conrey Retirement, 1972 (Box 42)
    - School of Education 50th Anniversary Celebration, 1972 (Box 42)
  - Video Tape
    - School of Education 75th Anniversary Program (VHS), 1997 (Box 42)
- Archived School of Education Website
  The Archived Website series documents the academic programs, accomplishments, resources, events, and people at the School of Education. Content includes important news and announcements, publications (such as newsletters and course catalogs), and information about admissions, curriculum, degree requirements, faculty, and the overall mission of the School. The website series is arranged chronologically, with captures from 2002 and 2003 stored on CD. Starting in 2010, this archived website will be captured on a regular, ongoing basis as part of the University of Michigan Web Archives, hosted at http://webarchives.cdlib.org/a/universityofmichigan/.
  - Website capture, May 15, 2002; 1 optical disks CDs (Box 2)
  - Website capture, May 22, 2003; 1 optical disks CDs (Box 2)
  - Archived School of Education home page, 2010-[ongoing]
  - Archived websites related to the School of Education, 2010-[ongoing]
Related Material
For additional records relating to the University of Michigan School of Education, researchers should consult the following record groups and personal papers collections, available at the Bentley Historical Library:
University of Michigan. Bureau of School Services
University of Michigan. Programs for Educational Opportunities
University of Michigan. University School
Fresh Air Camp (University of Michigan)
Cohen, Wilbur Joseph
Edmonson, James Bartlett
Lehmann, Charles Frederick
Olson, Willard Clifford
Rugen, Mabel
Whitney, Allen Sisson